<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Commune Concilium tentum in Camera Guildhall civitas London, die Jovis, quinto die Septembris, anno Dom. 1672 ... an Act for the Settlement and Well Ordering of Several Publick Markets within the City of London.</title>
            <title>Act for the Settlement and Well Ordering of Several Publick Markets within the City of London</title>
            <author>City of London (England).</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48997</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2854I</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39347</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18368517</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18368517</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48997)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1637:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Commune Concilium tentum in Camera Guildhall civitas London, die Jovis, quinto die Septembris, anno Dom. 1672 ... an Act for the Settlement and Well Ordering of Several Publick Markets within the City of London.</title>
                  <title>Act for the Settlement and Well Ordering of Several Publick Markets within the City of London</title>
                  <author>City of London (England).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Clark ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Broadside in 4 leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Guildhall, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Markets --  Law and legislation --  England --  London.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107420:1"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of the City of London</figDesc>
               </figure> Commune Concilium tentum in Camera <hi>Guildhall</hi> Civitatis <hi>London,</hi> die <hi>Jovis,</hi> quinto die <hi>Septembris,</hi> Anno Dom. 1672. Anno<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Regni Domini noſtri CAROLI Secundi, dei Gratia, <hi>Angliae, Scotiae, Franciae,</hi> &amp; <hi>Hiberniae</hi> Regis, Fidei Defenſoris, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> viceſimo quarto; coram <hi>Georgio Waterman,</hi> Milite, Majore Civitatis <hi>London, Ricardo Chiverton,</hi> Milite, <hi>Thoma Allen,</hi> Milite &amp; Baronetto, <hi>Johanne Frederick,</hi> Milite, <hi>Johanne Robinſon,</hi> Milite &amp; Baronetto, Locum-tenente Turris, <hi>Johanne Laurence,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ricardo Ford,</hi> Militibus, Aldermannis, <hi>Johanne Howel</hi> Milite, Serviente ad Legem ac Recordatore dictae Civitatis, <hi>Roberto Hanſon</hi> &amp; <hi>Willielmo Hooker,</hi> Militibus, <hi>Roberto Vyner,</hi> Milite &amp; Baronetto, <hi>Thoma Davis, Franciſco Chaplin,</hi> &amp; <hi>Jacobo Edwards,</hi> Militibus, Aldermannis, <hi>Patiente Ward,</hi> Armigero, Aldermanno, &amp; <hi>Roberto Clayton,</hi> &amp; <hi>Johanne Moore,</hi> Militibus, Aldermannis &amp; Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitibus dictae Civitatis, necnon majore parte Communiariorum de Communi Concilio ejuſdem Civitatis tunc &amp; ibidem aſſemblat. <hi>An Act for the Settlement and well Ordering of ſeveral Publick Markets within the City of</hi> LONDON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR the better Order and Regulation to be had of the Market at <hi>Leaden-hall,</hi> and the <hi>Greenyards</hi> there, with the other Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Grounds thereunto belonging; and of the Market at <hi>Woolchurch,</hi> and the Market of <hi>Honey-lane,</hi> or <hi>Milk-ſtreet,</hi> as alſo the Market near <hi>Newgate,</hi> and all other Common Markets already ſetled and appointed, or which hereafter ſhall be ſetled and appointed within the City of <hi>London:</hi> Be it Enacted by the Right Honourable the Lord Maior, and the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men his Brethren, and the Commons in this Common-Council Aſſembled, and by the Authority of the ſame, That the Rules, Orders, and Directions hereafter preſcribed, be duly obſerved by all perſons that are or may be concerned therein.</p>
            <p>And Firſt, whereas by former Acts of Common-Council, the ſale of Beef hath been reſtrained and appointed to be only in <hi>Leaden-hall,</hi> and the <hi>Greenyards</hi> there; which if now obſerved, would be very inconvenient to the Inhabitants of this City, in regard the late Butchery of the <hi>Stocks,</hi> and <hi>St. Nicholas-Shambles</hi> (which heretofore furniſhed with Beef and other Fleſh Victuals, thoſe parts of the City) are now removed and otherwiſe diſpoſed of: Be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all and every Butcher and Butchers, Poulterer and Poulterers (other then ſuch as are hereafter excepted) Country Farmer, Victualler, Lader, or Kidder, who keepeth no Butchers, or Poulterers Shop, or Shops within the City of <hi>London,</hi> or Liberties thereof, or within two Miles diſtance of the Liberties of the ſame City, may from and after the publication of this Act, take to Farm, or hire Standings, Stalls, or Places, in any the aforeſaid reſpective Markets; and there ſell, utter, and put to open ſhew, or ſale, his or their Beef, Mutton, Veal, Lamb, Pork, and other Butchery or Poultry Wares, or other Proviſions, upon the four days of the week, in manner as is hereafter expreſſed <hi>(viz.)</hi> upon <hi>Mondays, Wedneſdays,</hi> and <hi>Fridays</hi> weekly, between the Feaſt of the <hi>Annun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iation,</hi> and the Feaſt of <hi>St. Michael,</hi> from ſix of the Clock in the Forenoon,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107420:2"/> until eight of the Clock in the Evening of the ſame day; and between the Feaſt of <hi>St. Michael,</hi> and the <hi>Annuntiation,</hi> from eight of the Clock before noon, until five of the Clock in the Evening of the ſame day; and upon every Saturday in the Week all the Year long, from the aforeſaid reſpective hours of ſix and eight of the Clock before noon, until eight of the Clock in the Evening of the ſame day, for ſo long time only as he or they ſhall furniſh the ſaid Stalls, Standings, and Places with wholeſom Fleſh and other Proviſions in his or their own right, and not as Servant or Servants, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, in behalf of any others; any thing in any former Act of Common Council contained to the contrary thereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That no Butcher, or Poulterer whatſoever who keepeth no Shop or Shops within the City of <hi>London,</hi> or Liberties thereof, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two miles diſtance of the ſame City, ſhall in the ſaid reſpective Markets, ſell, utter, or put to open ſhew or ſale, his or their Butchery or Poultry Wares upon <hi>Mondays</hi> and <hi>Fridays</hi> weekly, upon pain that every ſuch Butcher, or Poulterer ſhall for every time he or they ſhall ſell, utter, or put to open ſhew or ſale in the ſaid Markets his or their Butchery, or Poultry Wares, upon <hi>Monday,</hi> or <hi>Friday</hi> in any week, forfeit the ſum of ten ſhillings.</p>
            <p>And to the end the reſpective hours aforeſaid may the better be obſerved in the ſaid Markets, It is further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Bell in all the ſeveral Markets within the City of <hi>London,</hi> ſhall Ring twice every day, (that is to ſay) the firſt Ringing from the twenty fifth of <hi>March,</hi> yearly, until the twenty ninth day of <hi>September,</hi> at ſeven of the Clock before noon, except upon <hi>Monday,</hi> and then the firſt Ringing ſhall not begin till eight of the Clock in the Forenoon: and from the twenty ninth day of <hi>September</hi> yearly, until the twenty fifth day of <hi>March,</hi> at eight of the Clock before Noon, and not before, except upon <hi>Monday,</hi> and then the firſt Ringing ſhall not begin till nine of the Clock before Noon; and that the ſecond Ringing of the Market Bell for raiſing of the ſaid Markets ſhall begin to Ring from and after the twenty fifth of <hi>March,</hi> yearly, until the twenty ninth day of <hi>September</hi> (except on <hi>Saturdays</hi>) half an hour after four in the Afternoon, and to continue Ringing till five of the Clock, and from and after the twenty ninth day of <hi>September,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the twenty fifth day of <hi>March</hi> yearly, (except on <hi>Saturdays</hi>) to begin to Ring half an hour after three of the Clock, and to continue Ringing until four of the Clock in the Afternoon: and that the ſecond Ringing of the Market Bell upon <hi>Saturday</hi> weekly throughout the year, ſhall begin half an hour after ſeven of the Clock, and to continue Ringing until eight of the Clock in the Evening of the ſame day. And if any Butcher, or Butchers, Poulterer, or Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, Victualler, Country Farmer, Lader, Kidder, or other perſon whatſoever, ſhall ſell, or put to open ſale any manner of Butchery, or Poultry Wares, or other Proviſions in the ſaid Markets, before Ringing of the Market Bell at the ſaid ſeveral hours and times in the Mornings reſpectively; ſuch Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or Offenders ſhall be proceeded againſt, as foreſtallers of the Market, as by the Law in this caſe is directed and appointed. And that no Butcher, Poulterer, Victualler, Country Farmer, Lader, Kidder, or other perſon whatſoever, ſhall ſell or put to open ſale, any Butchery, or Poultry Wares, or other Proviſions, after the end of Ringing the Market Bell at the ſaid ſeveral hours in the Afternoon reſpectively, but ſhall then depart from the ſaid Markets, upon pain that every perſon ſelling Butchery, or Poultry Wares, or other Proviſions after the ſaid reſpective hours in the aforeſaid Markets, ſhall forfeit the ſum of ten ſhillings for every ſuch Offence. And if any Butcher, Poulterer Country Farmer, Lader, Kidder, or other perſon whatſoever, ſhall ſell, utter, or put to open ſale in the ſaid Markets, any manner of Fleſhmeat upon any other day or days then is before hereby limited and expreſſed, ſuch Butcher, Poulterer, Country Farmer, Lader, Kidder, or other perſon ſhall for every ſuch Offence forfeit the ſum of twenty Shillings.</p>
            <p>Provided always, that no Butcher, Poulterer, Country Farmer, Lader, Kidder, or other perſon whatſoever, ſhall upon the <hi>Saturday</hi> in any week bring into any of the ſaid Markets, any manner of Fleſh meat, after ſix of the Clock in the Afternoon, between the twenty fifth of <hi>March,</hi> and the twenty ninth of <hi>September,</hi> yearly; nor after four of the Clock in the Afternoon, between the twenty ninth of <hi>September,</hi> and the twenty fifth of <hi>March,</hi> upon pain of forfeiting the ſum of ten Shillings for every time any ſuch perſon ſhall bring into any of the ſaid Markets any manner of Fleſh meats, after the ſaid reſpective hours.</p>
            <p>And further be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That no Stall, Standing, or Place within any of the ſaid Markets ſhall from and after the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of this Act be letten or allotted to any Butcher or Poulterer, who doth or ſhall keep any Butchers or Poulterers Shop within the City of <hi>London,</hi> or Liberties thereof, or within two miles diſtance of the Liberties of the ſaid City, for ſo long time as he or they ſhall keep any Butchers, or Poulterers Shop within the limits aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And further, That no Butcher, Poulterer, or other perſon whatſoever ſhall have and enjoy more then two Stalls, Standings, or Places within any one of the Markets aforementioned, at one time.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That the Country people and others reſorting to the ſaid Markets, being not Butchers, not Poulterers, nor ſelling any manner of Fleſh meat, or Poultry, may ſtand, or ſit and vend their Herbs, Fruit, Eggs, Butter, and other ſuch like Proviſions, and Commodities in the Markets, upon every working day in the week, between the Feaſt of the <hi>Annuntiation,</hi> and the Feaſt of <hi>St. Michael</hi> the Arch-Angel, from ſeven of the Clock in the Morning, until five of the Clock in the Evening of the ſame day: and upon every working day between the Feaſt of <hi>St. Michael</hi> and the <hi>Annuntiation,</hi> from ſix of the Clock in the Morning, until four of the Clock in the Evening of the ſame day, ſo as the ſame perſons that bring them firſt to Market do continue the ſelling thereof, and do obſerve the Ringing of the Market Bel or keeping the ſaid hours accordingly.</p>
            <p>And it is alſo further Enacted (in regard that the Market is moſt principally intended for the benefit of Houſe-keepers, who buy for their own uſe and behoof) That the Retailers and Traders of this City, who buy to ſell again, ſhall not enter into any of the aforeſaid Markets, to make their Proviſions, and buy of any of the Market people there, to carry the ſame to their ſeveral Houſes and Shops, until the Afternoon of every day, to the end that Houſe-keepers may provide themſelves in the morning of every day at the firſt hand and pay moderate Rates for their Proviſions; upon pain that every ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailer, or Retailers, or Traders, ſhall for every time Offending herein, forfei forty ſhillings.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as all dead Fleſh meat and other Victuals, and Proviſions of all ſorts of Fruits, Herbs, Fiſh, and the like, ought to be ſold in open and common Markets, allowed and appointed, and not under private Stalls or at Tavern doors, or in any Street or Common Paſſages, or in any
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107420:3"/> private Places, or carried up and down, and ſold by way of Hawking; by means whereof, much unwholſome Proviſions, dangerous to the Health and Bodies of his Majeſties Subjects, may be uttered and ſold: Be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That no Butcher, Poulterer, Country Farmer, Lader, Kidder, Victualler, Gardener, Fruiterer, Fiſh-ſeller, or other perſon or perſons whatſoever, ſhall from and after the publication of this Act, ſell, utter, or put to ſhew or ſale, by way of Hawking, or as a Hawker, or in any otherwiſe, any Beef, Mutton, Lamb, Veal, Pork, Poultry, Butter, Cheeſe, Fiſh, Fruit, Herbs, or other Victuals, or Proviſion whatſoever, in any private Houſe, Lane, Ally, Inn, Warehouſe, Street-ſtall, or Common Paſſage, or other place or places whatſoever, within the City of <hi>London,</hi> or Liberties thereof, but only in his or their open Shop, or Shops, or in the publick Market place, or places, and in Market time only, according as is before appointed, upon pain that every ſuch perſon ſo carrying, or offering to put to ſale, by way of Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or in any otherwiſe, any Fleſh meat, Poultry, or other Victuals whatſoever, as aforeſaid, in any private Houſe, Lane, Ally, Inn, Warehouſe, Street-ſtall, or Common Paſſage, or other places whatſoever, being not his, or their open Shop, or Shops, or the Common Market-place, ſhall forfeit the ſame Goods ſo offered to ſale, without any manner of favour, according to the antient Cuſtom of the City of <hi>London,</hi> uſed and approved; and the ſame ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited, ſhall be diſpoſed of to ſuch Priſons within this City of <hi>London,</hi> as the Lord Maior for the time being ſhall direct and appoint.</p>
            <p>And to the intent that Foreſtalling, Regrating, and Ingroſſing of Victuals, and other Commodities may be the better prevented, and the Laws made againſt the ſame more effectually obſerved, It is Declared and Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That no perſon, or perſons, from and after the publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Act, ſhall buy, or cauſe to be bought, any Victuals, or other things whatſoever, within the ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> or Liberties thereof, coming to any the Common Markets of this City, or make any Bargain, Contract, or Promiſe, for the having and buying of the ſame, or any part thereof, ſo coming as aforeſaid, before the ſame ſhall be brought into one of the ſaid Markets, ready to be there ſold: And alſo, That no perſon, or perſons that ſhall by any means Regrate, Obtain, or Get into his or their Hands, or Poſſeſſion, in any the ſaid Markets, any Victuals or other things whatſoever, that ſhall be thither brought to be ſold, ſhall from henceforth ſell the ſame again in their Shop, or Shops, or any of the Markets, or other places within this City and Liberties thereof, or ſhall Ingroſs, or Get into his or their Hands, by buying, contracting, or otherwiſe, any of the things aforeſaid, in the ſaid Markets, with intent to ſell the ſame again, in the ſame, or any other Markets, or places within this City, and Liberties thereof, upon pain that every ſuch Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaller, Regrater, and Ingroſſer, ſhall for every ſuch Offence, forfeit forty ſhillings.</p>
            <p>And whereas, for Accommodation of Market people, with Stalls, Boards, Shelter, and all other like things neceſſary for their Standing in any of the Market-places within the City of <hi>London,</hi> and cleanſing and keeping clean the ſame; and otherwiſe for defraying the incident Charges of Repairing and Maintaining the ſame Markets, and to Gratifie and Reward the Care and Attendance of ſuch perſons as ſhall be imployed therein, there hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been given and paid certain reaſonable Rates for the ſaid Accommodations and Charges: And to the intent that the ſaid Rates may be aſcertained and made publick to all Market people, whereby the perſons that ſhall from henceforth, by Order of the Committee for Letting of the City Lands, with Approbation of this Court, be imployed therein, as Collectors, or Receivers of the ſame Rates, may be prevented from Demanding, or Extorting more then is allowed, as is herein after expreſſed: Be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all and every perſon, and perſons, reſorting to any of the ſaid Markets, to ſell, and vend their Commodities, ſhall from henceforth pay unto ſuch perſon, or perſons, as from time to time ſhall be thereunto appointed, as aforeſaid, to take and receive the Profits of all, or any of the ſaid Markets, to the Vſe of the Maior, Commonalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> of, and from all Market people thereunto reſorting, for their Stalls, Standings, and other Accommodations, in the ſeveral Market-places aforeſaid, after the Rates following (that is to ſay) for every Stall, or Standing of the length of eight Foot, and breadth of four Foot, uſed or imployed for ſale of Fleſh meat, or Fiſh, for every day eight pence, or two ſhillings ſix pence <hi>per</hi> week; and for every ſuch Stall or Standing, uſed or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for ſale of any other Commodities, for every day four pence, or eighteen pence <hi>per</hi> week; and for every Stall, or Standing of the length of ſix foot, and breadth of four foot, uſed or imployed for the ſale of Fleſh meat, or Fiſh, ſix pence for every day, or two ſhillings <hi>per</hi> week; and for every ſuch Stall, or Standing uſed for other Proviſions, or Commodities, for every day, three pence, or ſixteen pence <hi>per</hi> week; and for every Standing for Tanned Leather, ſix pence <hi>per</hi> day; and for every raw Hide, an half peny; and for every Horſe Load of any Proviſions or Commodities not upon Stalls, three pence; and for every Cart-load of ſuch Commodities, ſix pence.</p>
            <p>Provided that all Gardeners, and Country people, and others reſorting to the ſaid Markets, early in the Morning, to ſell Herbs, Fruit, and other like Commodities, and there continue for no long ſpace, quitting the Markets at eight or nine of the Clock in the Morning, ſhall pay for the Larger Places or Standings, only three pence, for every time they reſort thither; and for the Leſſer Places, or Standings, only two pence.</p>
            <p>And that the ſaid Collectors, or Receivers ſhall not Demand or Require of the Market people more then according to the aforeſaid Rates, without the free Conſent and Agreement of the ſaid Market people, for ſome extraordinary Conveniency, or Accommodation, unleſs in <hi>Leaden-hall</hi> Market, where other and larger Rates have been anciently payed for Stalls, or Standings therein; and that no perſon, or perſons Inhabiting in or near to any the ſaid Market places, or other perſon or perſons whatſoever, upon pretence of any right whatſoever, other then the Receivers, or Collectors of the ſaid Rates and Duties, ſhall from henceforth provide any Stalls, or other Accommodations in any of the aforeſaid Market-places; or directly, or indirectly take, require, or exact any ſum, or ſums of mony, or other Reward of the Market people, for any Stalls, Standings, or Accommodation of their place, and ſtation in the ſaid Markets; upon pain that every perſon offending herein ſhall forfeit and loſe, for every time ſo doing and offending, twenty ſhillings.</p>
            <p>And for the better Order and Quiet of the Market people, and the reconciling all Differences that may ariſe therein, betwixt them and the Collectors, or Receivers in the aforeſaid Markets; as alſo that the Rates and Duties may be the better collected, and certainly paid into the Chamber of <hi>London,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fraud, and the ſaid Markets, more effectually ſuperviſed; for prevention of Abuſes and Diſorders that may ariſe therein, Be it Enacted, That the Committee for Letting the City Lands for the time being, ſhall and are hereby Authorized from time to time, by and with the Approbation of this Court,
<pb facs="tcp:107420:4"/> to appoint fitting perſons for Overſeers of the ſaid reſpective Markets, and Collectors, or Receivers of the Profits, or Duties ariſing, or growing out of the ſame; and to Treat, and Agree with the ſaid perſons, and allow them for their Care and Pains, ſuch part or portion of the ſaid Profits, as in their diſcretions ſhall be found requiſite: provided the ſaid Allowance exceed not the tenth part of the whole clear Profits (all neceſſary Charges being deducted) upon condition that the ſaid Overſeers and Collectors, or Receivers that ſhall from time to time be thereunto appointed, by order as aforeſaid, do give ſufficient ſecurity to the ſatisfaction of the ſaid Committee, for their Diligence and faithful Performance in their Office, and overſeeing the Orders and Proviſions aforeſaid, obſerved, and giving a juſt and true accompt of their Receipts and Payments of the Moneys every week into the Chamber; and that the ſaid Committee do once in every week meet together at the <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> and then and there audite the Accompts and Payments of the ſaid Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers, and Collectors, or Receivers, for prevention of any abuſes that by neglect thereof might ariſe or happen; and alſo endeavour, upon any Complaints, and Grievances of the Market people, againſt the ſaid Overſeers, and Collectors, or Receivers, or otherwiſe, to compoſe and redreſs the ſame as ſoon as poſſibly they can; that ſo all diſturbances to the Market people, and unneceſſary Suits at Law may be avoided: and that the ſaid Overſeers and Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or Collectors ſhall frequently attend, and be in the ſaid Markets, during Market time, and diligently overſee the ſame; to prevent with their beſt care, any abuſes or diſorders that may happen, or be committed therein; and alſo to take care that the Proviſions and Penalties appointed by this Act againſt all Offenders, contrary to the ſame, be duly and conſtantly put in Execution: and if any of the ſaid Overſeers, and Collectors, or Receivers ſhall be remiſs, or corrupt herein, then they ſhall be forthwith diſplaced, and diſabled of any Office, or Place touching the ſaid Markets.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted, That in caſe the aforeſaid Committee for Letting the City Lands, ſhall at any time hereafter and it moſt fitting, and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous for the benefit of the Chamber, to let the ſaid Markets, or any of them to Farm; that then the Committee aforeſaid, for the time being, ſhall and may treat with any perſon, or perſons for Letting the ſame to Farm, upon the beſt terms they can, and report their proceedings unto this Court for their Approbation therein.</p>
            <p>All which Pains, Forfeitures, and Penalties, Sum and Sums of Mony to be forfeited, by virtue of this Act, ſhall be recovered by Action of Debt, Bill, or Plaint to be Commenced and Proſecuted in the Name of the Chamberlain of the City of <hi>London,</hi> for the time being, in the Court holden before the Maior, and Aldermen in the Chamber of the <hi>Guild-hall</hi> of the City of <hi>London;</hi> and that the Chamberlain of the ſaid City for the time being in all Suits to be proſecuted by virtue of this Act, againſt any Offender, or Offenders, contrary to the ſame, ſhall recover the ordinary Coſts of Suit to be expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in and about the proſecution thereof; and if the Suit paſs for the Defendant, then the ſaid Defendant to recover his Coſts; and that the Chamberlain for the time being ſhall not have power to take leſs of any Offender then herein is limited to be forfeited for every Offence.</p>
            <p>And further, That one moiety of all Forfeitures to be recovered by virtue hereof (the Coſts of the Suit for Recovery of the ſame being deducted) ſhal after Recovery, and the Receipt thereof, at or before the twenty fifth day of <hi>March</hi> yearly, be paid and delivered unto the Treaſurer of <hi>Chriſts Hoſpital</hi> to be imployed towards the Relief of the Poor Children, to be brought up and maintained in that Hoſpital; and the other moiety to him or them which ſhall firſt give Information of the Offences, for which the Forfeitures ſhall grow; and proſecute Suit in the Name of the Chamberlain of the ſaid City for recovery of the ſame, any thing in this Act to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Serjeant, and Yeoman of the Channel, and Yeoman of <hi>Newgate-Market,</hi> and Foreign-taker, while the Common Markets were kept in <hi>Leadenhal-ſtreet, Cheapſide,</hi> and <hi>Newgate-ſtreet,</hi> did take care for ſweeping and making clean the ſaid Streets where the Market people reſorted, and paid for carrying away the Soil thereof; as alſo for furniſhing the Market people with Boards, and other Accommodations. In conſideration whereof they received ſome certain allowance by conſent of the Market people for their care and pains therein. Now foraſmuch as the ſaid Markets are removed out of the Streets, and made Commodious, at the publick Charge of the City, and that the Revenue thereof ought to be improved for the benefit of the Chamber: Be it Enacted, That the ſeveral Officers aforementioned, ſhall from henceforth be wholly diſcharged from the Charge of Cleanſing and Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rying away the Soil of the ſaid Markets, and providing Boards and other Accommodations for the Market people, and likewiſe from any ways inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>medling with the Receipt of any Duties, Fees, or Profits, or taking any Mony of any Perſons reſorting to, or ſtanding in any of the Common Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kets aforeſaid, upon any pretence whatſoever; but that inſtead thereof the Serjeant and Yeoman of the Channel for the time being ſhall, during their Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuance in the ſaid places, each of them, have and receive out of the Chamber of <hi>London,</hi> the ſum of three pounds weekly; and <hi>Richard Robinſon</hi> the preſent Foreign-taker, and Yeoman of <hi>Newgate-market,</hi> the ſum of three pounds every week, during the term of his natural Life: All which ſums reſpectively, and none other, ſhall be paid by the Chamberlain out of the Profits ariſing by the Markets, to the perſons aforeſaid, in full ſatisfaction of all their Right, Title, Claim, and Demand whatſoever, to any part or ſhare of the Profits to be Collected of the Market people.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed by <hi>Andrew Clark,</hi> Printer to the Honourable City of <hi>LONDON,</hi> at his Houſe in <hi>Alderſgateſtreet.</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
